[
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "If a solid has a low melting point and dissolves readily in benzene, it would probably",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "contain strong electrostatic forces of attraction",
            "conduct electricity in the molten state",
            "dissolve in water",
            "have covalent bonding",
            "absorb moisture on exposure to air"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "Which of the following molecules is linear in shape?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "CH<sub>4</sub>",
            "H<sub>2</sub>O",
            "NH<sub>3</sub>",
            "H<sub>2</sub>S",
            "CI<sub>2</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "Which of the following cannot be deduced from the electronic configuration of a transition metal?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "Possession of magnetic property",
            "Ability to form complex ions",
            "Position in the Periodic Table",
            "Variable oxidation states",
            "Physical properties of the metal"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "What is the percentage by mass of copper in copper in copper (l) oxide (CU<sub>2</sub>O)? [O = 16; CU =64]",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "88.9%",
            "80.0%",
            "66.7%",
            "20.0%",
            "11.1%"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "A WEAK ACID IS ONE WHICH",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "IS NOT CORROSIVE",
            "IS SLIGHTLY IONIZIED IN WATER",
            "DOES NOT PRODUCE SALTS WITH ALKALIS",
            "DOES NOT CONDUCT AN ELECTRIC CURRENT IN AQUEOUS SOLUTION",
            "FORMS ACID SALTS WITH BASES"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "Which of the following species is always present in acidified water?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "NH<sup>+</sup><sub>4</sub>",
            "O<sup>2-</sup>",
            "HCI",
            "H<sup>3</sup>O<sup>+</sup>",
            "HNO<sub>3</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "The most suitable method for preparing lead (ll) chloride is by",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "action of dilute HCI on PbSO<sub>4</sub>",
            "acts of dilute HCI on lead",
            "action of dilute HCI on PbCO<sub>3</sub>",
            "bubbling chlorine into a solution of Pb(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>",
            "mixing aqueous solutions Pb(NO<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>and NaCI."
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "<p>A positive brown ring test indicates the presence of</p>",
        "explanation": "<p><em>Brown ring test</em> is used for the detection of nitrate ions in a solution. As the name suggests it detects presence of nitrate ions by formation of brown ring</p>",
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "NO<sub>3</sub>",
            "Fe<sup>3+</sup>",
            "SO<sup>2-</sup><sub>3</sub>",
            "CU<sup>+</sup>",
            "NO<sup>-</sup><sub>2</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "Consider the reaction represented by the equation below: XO + YO → X + YO<sub>2</sub>In the reaction, YO acts as",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "an acidic oxide",
            "a basic oxide",
            "a reducing agent",
            "a weak base",
            "an oxidizing agent"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "Alums are classified as",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "simple salt",
            "acid salts",
            "anhydrous salts",
            "double salts",
            "basic salts"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "Sodium chloride cannot conduct electricity in the solid state because it",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "is a normal salt",
            "is highly soluble in water",
            "is an electrovalent compound",
            "does not have any effect on litmus",
            "does not contain mobile ions"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "What mass of copper will be deposited by the liberation of Cu<sup>2+</sup>when 0.1F of electricity flows through an aqueous solution of a copper (ll) salt? [Cu = 64]",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "64g",
            "32g",
            "12.8g",
            "6.4g",
            "3.2g"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 13,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "What mass of copper will be deposited by the liberation of Cu<sup>2+</sup>when 0.1F of electricity flows through an aqueous solution of a copper (ll) salt? [Cu = 64]",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "64g",
            "32g",
            "12.8g",
            "6.4g",
            "3.2g"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 14,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "Which of the following is not correct of the reaction represented by the equation below? 2C<sub>(s)</sub>+ O<sub>2(g)</sub>→ 2CO<sub>(g)</sub>; ∆H = - xKJ",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "there is an increase in entropy ;",
            "There is anincrease in gaseous volume",
            "Carbon (lV) oxide is produced",
            "The oxidation number of carbon increases from 0 to +2",
            "The reaction is exothermic"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 15,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "H<sub>3</sub>O<sup>+</sup><sub>(aq)</sub>+ OH-<sub>(aq)</sub>→ 2H<sub>2</sub>O<sub>(l)</sub>. The heat change accompanying the process represented by the equation above is the heat of",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "neutralization",
            "formation",
            "solution",
            "dilution",
            "hydration"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 16,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "The following statements about graphite are correct except that it",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "is used as a lubricant",
            "has a network structure",
            "contains mobile free electrons",
            "is good conductor",
            "is an allotrope of carbon"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 17,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "Which of the following is hydrocarbons is unsaturated?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "Ethane",
            "Benzene",
            "Propane",
            "2 - methylbutane",
            "2,2,4-trimethylpentane"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 18,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "The following can be obtained directly from the destructive distillation of coal except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "ammoniacal liquor",
            "coke",
            "producer gas",
            "coal gas",
            "coal tar"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 19,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "Fructose and glucose are classified as carbohydrates because they",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "are crystalline white solids",
            "are energy -giving substances",
            "are naturally occurring organic compounds",
            "contain carbon oxygen and hydrogen",
            "conform to the general formula C<sub>x</sub>(H<sub>2</sub>O)<sub>y</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 20,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "The gas produced when a mixture of sodium propanoate and soda lime is heated is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "methane",
            "pentane",
            "ethane",
            "butene",
            "ethyne"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 21,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "In which of the following processes are larger molecules broken down into smaller molecules?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "Vulcanization of rubber",
            "Hydrogenation of palm oil",
            "Hydrolysis of starch",
            "Polymerization",
            "Esterification"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 22,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "The following alkanols will yield alkanoic acids on reacting with excess acidified K<sub>2</sub>Cr<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OH",
            "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>2</sub>CHCH<sub>2</sub>OH",
            "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>CCH<sub>2</sub>OH",
            "(CH<sub>3</sub>)<sub>3</sub>COH",
            "CH<sub>3</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>CH<sub>2</sub>OH"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 23,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "Which of the following is an alloy of mercury?",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 3,
        "options": [
            "Stainless steel",
            "Soft solder",
            "Coinage bronze",
            "Amalgam",
            "Duralumin"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 24,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "The function of limestone in the extraction of iron in the blast furnace is",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "removal of the earthly impurities",
            "decomposition of the iron ore",
            "conversion of iron (lll) to iron (ll) compounds",
            "generation of heat for the process",
            "conversion of coke to carbon(ll)oxide"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 25,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "Metals which react with steam only when they are red-hot include",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 4,
        "options": [
            "copper",
            "sodium",
            "calcium",
            "gold",
            "iron"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 26,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "Copper (ll) tetraoxosulphate (VI) is often added to swimming pools because it",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 0,
        "options": [
            "prevents the growth of algae",
            "coagulates suspended particles",
            "neutralizes dissolved gases in water",
            "reacts with any excess chlorine present",
            "increases the amount of dissolved oxygen"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 27,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "The following salts dissolve readily in cold water except",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 1,
        "options": [
            "CaCI<sub>2</sub>",
            "PbSO<sub>4</sub>",
            "(NH<sub>4</sub>)<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>4</sub>",
            "Na<sub>2</sub>CO<sub>3</sub>",
            "Na<sub>2</sub>SO<sub>3</sub>"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 28,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "What is the amount (in mole) of hydrogen gas that would be produced if 0.6 mole of hydrochloric acid reacted with excess zinc according to the following equation? Zn<sub>(s)</sub>+ 2HCI<sub>(aq)</sub>→ ZnCI<sub>2(aq)</sub>+ H<sub>2(g)</sub>",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "0.1 mole",
            "0.2mole",
            "0.3 mole",
            "1.0 mole",
            "2.9 moles"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    },
    {
        "course": "chemistry",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 29,
        "year": 1995,
        "question": "What is the amount (in mole) of hydrogen gas that would be produced if 0.6 mole of hydrochloric acid reacted with excess zinc according to the following equation? Zn<sub>(s)</sub>+ 2HCI<sub>(aq)</sub>→ ZnCI<sub>2(aq)</sub>+ H<sub>2(g)</sub>",
        "explanation": null,
        "correctIndex": 2,
        "options": [
            "0.1 mole",
            "0.2mole",
            "0.3 mole",
            "1.0 mole",
            "2.9 moles"
        ],
        "type": "objectives"
    }
]